Lawrence E. Glendenin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lawrence E. Glendenin Papers 1935-2009 (bulk 1945-1975)
MSS85456
Glendenin, Lawrence E. (Lawrence Elgin), 1918-2008
850 items
3 containers
1.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Nuclear chemist and co-discoverer of Promethium, element 61 on the periodic table of elements. Subject files, correspondence, writings, speeches, biographical material, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and awards documenting Glendenin's work on the Manhattan Project, the Bikini Scientific Resurvey, and his career at Argonne National Laboratory.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Glendenin, Lawrence E. (Lawrence Elgin), 1918-2008.; Marinsky, Jacob A. (Jacob Akiba), 1918-2005.; Smyth, Henry De Wolf, 1898-1986. A general account of the development of methods of using atomic energy for military purposes under the auspices of the United States government, 1940-1945. 1945.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Organizations
Argonne National Laboratory.; Bikini Scientific Resurvey.; Manhattan Project (U.S.); Oak Ridge National Laboratory.
Subjects
Atomic bomb--United States.; Nuclear weapons--Research--United States.; Promethium.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Titles
Lawrence Elgin Glendenin papers
Occupations
Nuclear chemists.
Provenance
The papers of Lawrence E. Glendenin, nuclear chemist and co-discoverer of Promethium, were given to the Library of Congress by Charles D. Glendenin in 2009-2010.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Lawrence E. Glendenin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1918, Nov. 8 Born, Bay City, Mich.
1941 S.B. in chemistry, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1942 Joined the University of Chicago’s Metallurgical Laboratory (code name for the Manhattan Project) as a member of Charles D. Coryell's team, Chicago, Ill.
1943 1945 Transferred to Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tenn.
1945 Discovered with Jacob A. Marinsky, Promethium, the 61st element on the periodic table One of sixty-seven Oak Ridge Laboratory scientists who signed the Oak Ridge petition calling for President Harry S. Truman to describe and demonstrate the atomic bomb's power and give Japan the opportunity to surrender Married Ethel Long
1946 1949 Ph.D. in nuclear chemistry, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1947 Patent issued for Brady-Glendenin safety pipette Member of radio chemistry team, Bikini Scientific Resurvey, studying effects of atomic bomb testing on the Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands)
1949 1985 Senior scientist, Chemistry Division, Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Ill.
1958 Visiting scientist, Metallurgy Division, Harwell Laboratory, Oxon, United Kingdom
1963 Appointed scientific secretary, United States delegation to the International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, Geneva Switzerland
1974 American Chemical Society Award for Nuclear Applications in Chemistry
2008 Died, Nov. 22, Crystal Lake, Ill.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lawrence E. Glendenin (1918-2008) span the years 1935-2009, with the bulk concentrated in the period 1945-1975. The papers consist of correspondence, writings, subject files, and printed matter. The collection contains material on the Bikini Scientific Resurvey, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, and Glendenin and Jacob A. Marinsky's discovery of Promethium, the 61st element on the periodic table. The collection also contains material on the Oak Ridge petition written by Oak Ridge scientists in 1945 following review and debate of a petition by Leo Szilard calling for President Harry S. Truman to describe and demonstrate the atomic bomb's power and then offer Japan the opportunity to surrender. The collection includes the Smyth report, an administrative history of the Manhattan Project by physicist Henry DeWolf Smyth. The report was published on August 12, 1945, under its official name, A General Account of the Development of Methods of Using Atomic Energy for Military Purposes.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is grouped into a subject file and a writings file and arranged alphabetically thereunder by topic, name of person, organization, or type of material.
Container List
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - American Chemical Society (Box 1)
    - Award for Nuclear Applications in Chemistry, 1973-1974 See also Awards and honors, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Coryell, Charles D., regarding, 1974-1976 See also Container 2, Coryell, Charles D. (Box 1)
    - Symposium on the Commemoration of the Discovery of Fission, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Symposium in memory of Ellis P. Steinberg, 1992, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Ill., 1955-1958, 1977-1981, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Awards and honors, 1935-1941, 1949, 1974, 1989-1992 See also same container, Award for Nuclear Applications in Chemistry, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Bikini Scientific Resurvey, Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands), 1947, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Biographical information, 1976, 2000-2001, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, various, 1953-1960 (Box 2)
  - Coryell, Charles D., 1954, 1968-1971 See also Container 1, same heading (Box 2)
  - Gest, Howard, 1990 (Box 2)
  - International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, Geneva, Switzerland, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass., 1946-1949, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tenn. (Box 2)
    - Certificates, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Smyth report, 1945 (Box 2)
    - ORNL Review, 1976 See also same container, Promethium (Box 2)
    - Printed matter, 1945-1946, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Promethium See also same container, ORNL Review (Box 2)
    - Evans, C. H., 1989-1992 (Box 2)
    - Printed matter, 1942-1949, 1981, 1989, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Seaborg, Glenn T., 1967-1980, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Steinberg, Ellis P., 1991-1992, undated (Box 3)
  - Szilard petition and Oak Ridge petition, 1945, 1967, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Youth outreach, talks and interviews, 1989-2002 (Box 3)
- Writings file (Box 3)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box 3)
  - By Glendenin, 1948, 1961 (Box 3)
  - By Glendenin with others, 1946-1955, 1965 (Box 3)
  - By others (Box 3)
    - Griffin, Henry C., 2003 (Box 3)
    - Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, Los Alamos, N. Mex. (Box 3)
    - Mouze, Genevieve, Sabet Hachem and Christian Ythier, 2008-2009 (Box 3)
    - Smyth, Henry D., 1945-1946 (Box 3)